Guide to the International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9 Records WAG.150
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9 Records
1932-2000
1972-1988
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City
Vagelatos, Sandy
WAG.150
5 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons.
The membership of the International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9 in the New York City metropolitan area has generally reflected the various waves of immigrants coming into the country, the development of different political tendencies in the labor movement, and the tensions brought on by changes in the U.S. economy. The Council has also been the site of important struggles against racketeering and corruption, and for union democracy. The collection consists of bound minute books, agreements with other trade unions and legal documents relating to Frank Arnold, James Bishop, and Frank Schonfeld, among others. Correspondence, election materials, photographs Trusteeship records and Executive Trial Board records of Frank Schonfeld's trial (1972) are also included.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Sandy Vagelatos (Business Manager and Secretary-Treasurer of the Council) on behalf of the International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9 in 2001. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2001.088, 2001.146, and NPA 2001.088.
The accession number 2018.029 is also associated with this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Founded in 1887 as the Brotherhood of Painters and Decorators of America and also known as the Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators and Paperhangers of America, the International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9 (IBPAT DC 9) quickly rose to a prominent position in New York City and the surrounding area. Its membership generally reflected the various waves of immigrants coming into the country, the development of different political tendencies, and the tensions brought on by changes in the U.S. economy.
After a series of conflicts with rival union the Amalgamated Association of Painters and Decorators, the Painters District Council 9 added the Alteration Painters Union (with branches in Harlem, the Lower East Side, Brooklyn and the Bronx) to its ranks in 1914.
Racketeers were a major force in Painters District Council 9 (as they were in many other NYC building trades unions) until the membership, under the leadership of Louis Weinstock's Communist Party-oriented administration, attempted to break their hold in the 1930s. Weinstock's alliance (with its base in the Rank-and-File Clubs) had its own drawbacks, and some members felt that their interests were neglected in favor of the CP's all-out efforts in support of World War II, including the no-strike pledge.
In 1946, the Progressive Painters Club ran Martin Rarback as a new reform candidate for secretary-treasurer of the District, and he won the post in 1947. Rarback's promised militant program led to some progressive changes in the union, but he soon became party to dubious practices that pre-dated his administration.
After 1947, the Rank-and-File Club carried on its opposition fight, but the Cold War political climate and the conservative drift of the labor movement made for an uphill battle, and the group experienced several years of setbacks, including the expulsion of its key leaders from the union. In spite of undercurrents of discontent, there were no contested district-wide elections from 1953 to 1961, and the Rank-and-File Club was barely able to maintain its presence in a few locals.
By 1961, Rarback's blatant favoritism had created such dissatisfaction among members that organized opposition reasserted itself for the first time in many years. Reconstructing an opposition movement was hard work. Frank Schonfeld ran for District Council 9 secretary-treasurer in 1961. He lost, but did so with 42% of the vote, a considerable turnout against Rarback's machine. The day after the 1961 election, the Rarback administration sued Schonfeld and others for libel, and Schonfeld lost his job.
Nevertheless, pressure from Schonfeld and other dissidents within District Council 9 forced the International, which in general supported the incumbent administration, to step in and impose a trusteeship in DC 9, a move that served to buffer the Rarback machine. Schonfeld was blocked from running for election in 1964, but after successfully challenging the trusteeship, he was elected as DC 9 secretary-treasurer in a supervised, district-wide election in 1967.
Opposed almost continually during the two terms he served, Schonfeld was ousted in 1973 by James Bishop, a candidate promoted by Rarback's Progressive Painters Club. Under threats made against him by members of the Lucchese Crime Family, Bishop resigned from his position in 1989, and was murdered by the mob in 1990. The ensuing investigation by city, state and federal law enforcement agencies revealed the layers of corruption that had pervaded the Council since Schonfeld's ouster, and most officers of District Council 9 were found guilty in state court on charges of racketeering.
Following these convictions, the entire administration of District Council 9 was forced out of office, and General President William Duval appointed John Alfarone, President and Business Manager of the Drywall and Tapers, Local 1974, as Trustee of the District Council. After eighteen months this trusteeship ended, and elections were held.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of bound minute books, agreements with other trade unions and legal documents relating to Frank Arnold, James Bishop, and Frank Schonfeld, among others. Correspondence, election materials, photographs Trusteeship records and Executive Trial Board records of Frank Schonfeld's trial (1972) are also included.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically in Series I and alphabetically in Series II and III.
The files are grouped into three series:
Series I: Minutes, 1968-1990
Series II: General Files, 1932-2000
Series III: Photographs, 1939-1991
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9 Records (WAG 150)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9: Trusteeship Records (WAG 149)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Local 490 Records (WAG 042)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Local 490 Photographs (PHOTOS 150)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Local 874 Records (WAG 152)
Frank Schonfeld Photographs (PHOTOS 144)
Daniel French Papers (WAG 101)
Frank Schonfeld Papers (WAG 027)
Sam Winn Papers (WAG 203)
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
New York (N.Y.); Correspondence.; Indictments (legal documents).; Legal documents.; Labor union democracy -- New York (State); Painters, Industrial -- New York (State) -- New York.; Painters, Industrial -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor unions -- Corrupt practices -- New York (State); Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs.; Collective labor agreements -- Painters, Industrial -- New York (State) -- New York.; Minutes (administrative records); Arnold, Frank; Astor, Vincent, 1891-1959; Bishop, James; Schonfeld, Frank; Rarback, Martin; Alfarone, John; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City; Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America. Local 490 (New York, N.Y.); Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America. Local 848 (New York, N.Y.); International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City; Vagelatos, Sandy
- Series I: Minutes, 1968-1990
  - Minutes, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes (I), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes (II), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Minutes (I), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minutes (II), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes: Trustees Meeting Re: Pension, 1974-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: Trustees Meeting Re: Pension, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series II: General Files, 1932-2000
  - Agreement: Astor, Vincent (Newsweek Building) and DC 9, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Agreement: Carnegie Hall and Maintenance Division, Building and Construction Trades Council, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Agreement: Garfinkel, Sam and Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators and Paperhangers of America, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Agreement: Local Union of Connecticut State Conference of Painters Affiliates of IBPAT and "Employer", 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Agreement: Trade Agreements, IBPAT with other unions, 1965-1968, 1987-1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Agreement and Correspondence: Painting Industry Pension Fund of New York and IBPAT National Pension Fund Merger, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Anniversary Dinner, 100th: Program and Invitations, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Arnold, Frank F. v. DC 9 and IBPAT: Appellant's Appendix, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Arnold, Frank F. v. DC 9 and IBPAT: Briefs, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bishop, James: Testimony, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Board of Arbitration: IBPAT v. Hubbard Painting and Decorating, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Board of Arbitration: Plasterers Local 60 v. DC 9, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Board of Arbitration: Pointers, Caulkers and Cleaners Local Union 66 v. DC 9, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Board of Arbitration: United Union of Roofers, Waterproofers and Allied Workers Local Union 8 v. DC 9, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - By-Laws, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Calendars, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Clippings: Re: Jack "Legs" Diamond, Jacob Wellner, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Clippings: Scrapbook, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Convention, 25th General: Fifth Day Session, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1953, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence: Re: Astor, Vincent (Newsweek Building), 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence: Re: Charles F. Noyes Co. Inc., 1948-1948 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: Re: Dispute over spray application of simulated acoustical material on ceilings, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence: Re: Eastern Offices, Inc., 1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Re: Gimbel Brothers, 1937, 1940, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Raftery, S. Frank, 1972-1973, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Wolford, James, 1971-1973, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Draft Resolutions, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dues Books: Hollander, Harry, 1939-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dues Books: Smolar, Julius, 1933-1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Election Materials: Bishop, James and Schonfeld, Frank, 1972, 1976, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Election Materials: Flyers: English-Yiddish, 1939-1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Election Materials: Flyers and Ballots, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Election Materials: Flyers and Clippings: English-Italian, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Election Materials: Flyers and Correspondence, 1973-1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Election Materials: "Painters Free Press", 1972, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Election Materials: Sample Ballots, 1936-1976 (Box Shared Tamiment 007, Folder 6)
  - Executive Trial Board: DC 8 et al. v. General Vice President Michael E. Monroe, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Executive Trial Board: Schonfeld Trial (I), 1972 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Executive Trial Board: Schonfeld Trial (II), 1972 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Executive Trial Board: Schonfeld Trial (III), 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Executive Trial Board: Schonfeld Trial (IV), 1972 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Executive Trial Board: Schonfeld Trial (V), 1972 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Executive Trial Board: Schonfeld Trial (VI), 1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Executive Trial Board: Schonfeld Trial (VII), 1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Executive Trial Board: Schonfeld Trial (VIII), 1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Executive Trial Board: Schonfeld Trial: General, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Executive Trial Board: Suggestions for Proper Conduct of Trials, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Health and Safety Guides, 1993, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - IBPAT et al. v. DC 9 et al.: Findings, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - IBPAT et al. v. DC 9 et al.: Notice of Cross Motion and Affidavit of James Bishop; Paint Pot (newsletter, with report on Bishop Reinstatement), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Joint Trade Board: Decision Records, 1990-1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Joint Trade Board: Hearing Re: Norvic Painting Company, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Local Union 490: Commemorative Programs, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Local Union 490: Re: Paperhangers Strike, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Local Union 806: Collective Bargaining Agreement with Steel Painters Contractors Association, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Local Union 806: Correspondence, 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Local Union 1456: Minutes, 1944-1949 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Mercury Paint Company v. Keystone Painting Company et al.: Correspondence, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - New York City Transportation Administration: Rules and Regulations for Employees, Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - NY Painter, clippings, broadsides, 1934-1970 (Box Shared Tamiment 007, Folder 7)
  - Pension Fund: Annual Report, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Pension Fund: International Foundation of Employee Benefit Plans Report, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Prevailing Wage Law: Barbaro-Brodsky Report, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Prevailing Wage Law: Violation Complaint Form, Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Programs: Testimonial Dinners: Levy, Murray and Wellner, Jacob, 1939, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Robbins, Harold, Morris Berger, Max Zasher and Frank Schonfeld v. James Bishop and Thomas Noschese, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Rosen, Max (aka Frank Robbins): Clipping, Oral History Transcript, Trial Board, Copies of Photographs, Undated, 1961, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 22a)
  - Schonfeld, Frank and Al Herman v. DC 9 et al.: Correspondence and Legal Documents, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Silverman, Daniel v. DC 9: National Labor Relations Board Complaint, Fine Art Decorating, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - State of New York v. DC 9: Corruption: Miscellaneous Documents, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Trusteeship Records: United States Department of Labor Report, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Trusteeship Records: Re: Woodfinishers Dispute with Carpenters, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Trusteeship Records: Hearing (I), 1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Trusteeship Records: Hearing (II), 1977 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Trusteeship Records: Hearing (III), 1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Trusteeship Records: Hearing (IV), 1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Trusteeship Records: Hearing (V), 1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Trusteeship Records: Hearing (VI), 1977 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Trusteeship Records: Hearing Re: Local Union 655, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Trusteeship Records: Post-Hearing Memorandum on Behalf of DC 9, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Work-for-Victory Day, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series III: Photographs, 1939-1991
  - Labor Day, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Labor Day and Pickets, circa 1991 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Portraits, 1939-1990s (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Repainting Prometheus (Rockefeller Center), 1974 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Work Sites, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - 22nd convention, 1969
- Series IV: Archived Website, May 3, 2009-ongoing
  Scope and Content Note
  The District Council 9 New York is local branch of the International Union of Painters and Allied Trades, chartered in 1900. District Council 9 is an organization of painters, decorators, wall covers, drywall finishers, sign painters, metal polishers, bridge & structural steel painters, civil service painters, lead abatement workers, glaziers & architectural metal glassworkers, paint makers, paint makers and allied trades. The website contains information on their apprencticeship programs, news, and event listings.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
- Unprocessed
  - VHS, hat, T-shirt (Box 1)